<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January XXX, 1675/6 by Henry Bagshaw ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12125945</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12125945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 756:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January XXX, 1675/6 by Henry Bagshaw ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid, and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54597:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT VVHITE-HALL, January <hi>xxx.</hi> 1675/6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY BAGSHAW,</hi> D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Botolphs Biſhopſgate,</hi> and Chaplain to the Lord HIGH-TREASURER of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> againſt the little North-door of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church. 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54597:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable THOMAS <hi>EARL of DANBY,</hi> Lord HIGH-TREASURER of ENGLAND, <hi>And One of the LORDS of His MAJESTIES</hi> MOST HONOURABLE PRIVY COUNCIL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have adventured upon the Publication of this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to the World, as a poor Teſtimony of my Obedience to Your Lordſhips Pleaſure. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs is my <hi>Subject;</hi> and the Great <hi>Example</hi> of it is a <hi>PRINCE,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Memory</hi> you pay <hi>homage.</hi> Religion <hi>ſhines</hi> in ſuch Inſtances, and borrows new <hi>Majeſty</hi> from the Pattern; nay Martyrdom it ſelf looks <hi>Royal,</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> (thus ſhed) paints its <hi>Glory.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:54597:3"/>It is one Miſtake in the World, to cry down Titles as <hi>meer Names;</hi> when as they produce Noble Effects, and are ſuch a <hi>ſhadow</hi> to <hi>Virtue,</hi> that they protect it by <hi>following.</hi> If Goodneſs gives <hi>Honour</hi> a real <hi>grace,</hi> Honour pays it back in <hi>opinion;</hi> therefore the uſefulneſs that is in it, renders it a fit Object of our <hi>regard:</hi> However alone it cannot profit the Perſons, without <hi>Goodneſs</hi> be joyned.</p>
            <p>You <hi>(MY LORD)</hi> have a great ſhare in Temporal Dignity: Your <hi>try'd worth</hi> has recommended You to Your Prince, and the ſtedfaſt <hi>Integrity</hi> of Your Actings: The firſt provokes <hi>Envy,</hi> and the ſecond <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> it. Your Faſtneſs to the <hi>CHURCH</hi> is as well known, and the employment of Your Power to <hi>oblige.</hi> May God continue You an Inſtrument in His Service, eſtabliſh You with His Grace, and preſerve in You a <hi>Goodneſs</hi> as well as <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of <hi>Name;</hi> which is the earneſt Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt obedient Servant and Chaplain, <hi>HENRY BAGSHAW.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54597:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM xxxvij. 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT has been a perplexing Queſtion in all Ages, and by all ſorts of Religions entertain'd; why Good and Evil ſhould be blended and mixt; and without any ſhow of choice diſpenſed amongſt Men in the ſecret courſe of God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence? This indifferency of acting in humane Affairs, has made Heathens to conclude, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54597:4"/>an uncertain Chance governs the World; nay, it has further prevailed upon true Worſhippers to ſuſpend the exerciſe of their Faith, though not utterly to deſtroy the root of it. And ſuch a kind of doubting the Church was ſubject to in <hi>David</hi>'s time; whence this <hi>Pſalm</hi> was written for their cure, who through weakneſs of fleſh took <hi>ſenſe</hi> for their guide, and the <hi>outward ſurface</hi> of things for their argument to build on. By the one they fell under a <hi>ſhortneſs of ſight;</hi> by the other they had <hi>emptineſs</hi> for their object. Therefore he ſets them in a ſure way of conſidering Events, and that is to <hi>mark</hi> and examin them with their underſtandings; to take their <hi>flight</hi> beyond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent appearances to the ends and periods of things; where the ſubſtance of Beings is diſcern'd, becauſe the truth of their ſtate is laid open. Otherwiſe we ſhould be all apt to miſtake, and ready to pronounce a falſe judgment.</p>
            <p>So a little before my Text, he acquaints us what imagination he had when he firſt ſaw the wicked man, whom he preſently compares to the <hi>green bay tree;</hi> as looking <hi>freſh and gay</hi> in the ornament of power, though <hi>blood</hi> likely was the <hi>moiſture</hi> that fed it. His <hi>lawrels</hi> and his <hi>crimes</hi> they flouriſhed together, and an impious hand became the planter of his glory; ſo that the Prophet thought at the firſt glimpſe the proſperity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54597:4"/>of his condition to be moſt deſirable: But lo! the <hi>exit</hi> of all; <hi>He paſſed by, and was not;
<note place="margin">Verſe 36.</note> yea I ſought him,</hi> (ſays the Pſalmiſt) <hi>but he could not be found:</hi> As if all that greatneſs he beheld, were rather ſome <hi>image</hi> in ſleep (where <hi>fancy</hi> ſports with its own <hi>creation)</hi> than a real object without, preſented to the beholder.</p>
            <p>Who is it now he oppoſes to that wicked man, or propounds to us devoutly to regard? It is the <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>upright</hi> Worſhipper; and the <hi>end</hi> he aſſigns him is <hi>peace,</hi> or a glorious reward, notwithſtanding thoſe ſeeming <hi>blaſts</hi> in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and the apparent ruins of his ſtate, when (like a Cedar cut down) he leaves upon the earth the ſad reverence of his fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright; for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know the <hi>Septuagint</hi> read theſe words in the abſtract, which is followed too by ſome other Tranſlations; but the <hi>Hebrew-Text,</hi> and the ſcope of the Pſalmiſt (not to ſpeak of our own Bibles) will juſtifie the ſenſe I have mentioned. And ſo I intend to handle them, where we may conſider three things:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, A Duty enjoyn'd: Mark and behold; that is, <hi>as from a watch-tower</hi> look far off and obſerve.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, The Subject wherein it is employ'd:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54597:5"/>The perfect and upright man; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes alſo the oppoſite party, the evil doer.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, The Fruit or Effect of this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: Which is to diſcern a diſtinctneſs of end, namely, the upright man's peace or reward; which neceſſarily ſuppoſes the others puniſhment.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall caſt the two firſt into one propoſition, which is this:</p>
            <p>That we ought to be heedful Obſervers of God's Providential Rule in the World, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of his Diſpenſation to his People.</p>
            <p>As for heeding his Rule in the general,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Uſefulneſs of the Work,</item>
                  <item>2. The Excellency of our Faculties calls for it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Uſefulneſs of the Work; ſince by an exactneſs of ſearch we diſcover not only a <hi>Hand</hi> of Power, but an <hi>Eye</hi> of Wiſdom, in turning the <hi>Wheel;</hi> where all the courſes of it are ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God's Glory, and the intricacy of its motions brings about the accompliſhment of his Deſigns. The reſult of this Diſcovery is increaſe of Faith, ſettlement of Mind, and a cloſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency upon the Supreme. Do but regard the <hi>Throne</hi> above, you will regard too the <hi>Chain</hi> that is tyed to it; how immoveably God holds there
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54597:5"/>the <hi>Links</hi> of <hi>Cauſes,</hi> not to be broken off, nor alter'd, but by His ſpecial appointment. Did we thus mind the order of the whole Frame, the connexion of Events, and God's care to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what he has purpoſed, a Spirit of Atheiſm would quickly vaniſh; and the <hi>Light</hi> of that <hi>Theater</hi> we walk in, would at once convince and reform us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Excellency of our Faculties calls for ſuch a beholding. For God has planted in us <hi>contemplative</hi> powers as well as <hi>active;</hi> nay, the pure and ſpiritual exerciſe of the Soul lyes in the former. It is the ſubliming of our Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, the exalting of our Reaſon, the great prerogative of our Beings, to view God and his Works: He is continually viewing them and Himſelf; and we ſhow the nobleneſs of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent from Him, when thus employ'd in our <hi>ſpeculation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you regard the actions of Senſe, here Brutes do ſurpaſs us; and the pleaſures they enjoy, are more accurate, becauſe they have no higher per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to ſeek after: But the height of Man's Faculty, that leads him to the beſt Objects, it breaks the force of a ſenſual delight, ſince he has an intellectual Viſion to purſue. Now a chief part of this Viſion is God in his Providence; where the Mind is taken up with the ſight of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54597:6"/>Order and Beauty in the Creation; of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence and Knowledge in the Rule; of Labour and Conſpiracy in Beings to thoſe Ends appointed them; and having theſe things for its Idea's, it grows enlarg'd and beautified by what it receives. Whether then we attend to the advantage of the Employment, or the dignity of our own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we may eaſily conclude, that a <hi>conſidering ſpirit</hi> is required of us; which if laid aſide through any carnal temptation, Man thereby as well as his Intereſt is forſaken.</p>
            <p>Thus much briefly for <hi>marking Providence</hi> in the <hi>general</hi>— But that which more particularly binds us to obſerve, is <hi>God's Diſpenſation to his People.</hi> For God walks in his Church, as in a <hi>Garden</hi> of Pleaſure; He delights in thoſe <hi>Plants</hi> He ſets, prunes and dreſſes them, and ſhows by the ſingularity of His care, that they are the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of his Government. The World is but <hi>waſte ground,</hi> and altogether ſubject to a common influence; the Sun enlightens, the Wind blows, the Rain waters, but the true <hi>Husbandry</hi> is reſerv'd for the Paradiſe he has choſen. Here He has fix'd his Dwelling-place, and here He exhibits his loving-kindneſs; all the method of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline tending to the improvement of the <hi>Soil.</hi> Yet leſt we ſhould take wrong meaſures in our notice, as it relates to the governing of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54597:6"/>Children, theſe Rules muſt be followed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God, who preſcribes to Himſelf one method for eternally ſaving, preſcribes none for temporally ruling thoſe He ſaves. In the one, He acts like a <hi>Judge,</hi> where a certain <hi>order</hi> is ſet up; in the other, like a <hi>Soveraign,</hi> where a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>freedom</hi> is eſtabliſhed: So that the variety of models and forms, which are ſeen in the conduct of his People to happineſs, ought not to infer any neglect, but the uncontrollable liberty of his Power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That outward Bleſſings are not gifts of choice, nor the proper donatives of His hand. They may <hi>adorn</hi> indeed the uprightneſs of a cauſe, but not <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> it; which has ſurer characters to be known by, and a right founded upon better Titles, than an Idolater or an Uſurper can plead. We all find that even the worſt of Men can urge a ſucceſs, and the honour of that portion they enjoy, as a moſt plauſible defence of their actings; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if <hi>marks of Grace</hi> were not otherwiſe placed, God's love to his People would be loſt, nay the Juſtice of his Government deſtroyed. Thirdly, we muſt obſerve,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the End of his Government being <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> he carries it on ſometimes by <hi>inviſible</hi> ways, and leads his Servants thorough a dark
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54597:7"/>path, though at other times he draws out his <hi>Lights,</hi> I mean the <hi>miracles</hi> of his Protection, to confirm his Church in a Belief of his Promiſes. So then, his Methods being various, his outward Bleſſings undiſtinguiſhing, and his End ſpiritual in his Rule, our contemplation of a Saint ought to be pure and refin'd; abſtracted from thoſe accidents he meets with in the World; and how ſevere ſoever his changes he, yet our judgment upon them ſhould be unchangeable, fixt (like God's purpoſe) on his reward. The perception of things in Religion is at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> whereas Senſe requires a <hi>neerneſs</hi> of the Object. To take a proſpect of Nature, is to approach near to particulars; but to take a proſpect of God's Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is to ſtand a far off and behold. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no concluſion ought we to form, but by comprehending the <hi>Stage</hi> of the whole Life; we muſt not judge upon a preſent view of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, flight, routing of Armies, and an eclipſe of Glory (which the beſt of Princes has been ſubject to) but carry our Eye forward to the <hi>laſt enduring of the temptation,</hi> when <hi>he receives a crown of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What we are to mark in our Lord Chriſt, the ſame ſhould be obſerved in his Followers; firſt the Sufferings of the Croſs, and then the Triumphs of the Throne: To ſtop in the way, and divide
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54597:7"/>our proſpect, is to render it deformed; it is to fill it with <hi>ſhadows,</hi> and not with <hi>light;</hi> to view a hand in the cloud, gathering together <hi>ſtorms</hi> and no <hi>bleſsings.</hi> Whoever would think to know the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful proportions of any Being, muſt conſider it at the full, and not in the ſeparated and divided parts of it; ſo the work of Providence in gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Saint, ought entirely and perfectly to be looked upon. For we do but <hi>libel</hi> it by taking it in pieces, but we learn to <hi>adore</hi> it in the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> makes his Wiſeman to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Spectator of Beings and Events; and to enter into the World, as into an <hi>Olympick</hi> Game, there to regard all paſſages; but this neceſſarily does infer a ſuſpence of judgment 'till the prize be obtained; which ſhould he let looſe to all the accidents of the Combat, in ſtead of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom he would act folly; ſince it is the Eye of a Fool that is always ranging to an uncertainty. Who is there can poſſibly determin the conditions of Men from an immediate beholding of their courſe here? Does not God often ſhuffle humane Affairs, turn and caſt them, and make his outward Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in States a kind of mockery of Man's Knowledge, where the difference of perſons is loſt for ſome time, and conſequently the ability of diſcerning? If any difference be found, it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54597:8"/>that which offends; and that is, when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright Man falls, and (what adds weight to his overthrow) perhaps cauſed by the hand of ſome proſperous triumphing Malefactor; which ſeems at the firſt ſight, as ill an Object of contemplation, as the Picture of a Temple burnt and deſtroyed, with the Breaker up of that Temple paſſed by. Yet however it becomes a Chriſtian to mark, and to keep his Eye fixt in the midſt of turnings; the patience of Faith is expected from him in his ſtanding, that ſo the evidence of Faith may ſucceed.— Which brings me to the Third Particular in my Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fruit or Effect of this Obſervation. And that is to diſcern a diſtinctneſs of End betwixt the righteous and the wicked. For the end of the righteous is peace, or a glorious reward; which unavoidably ſuppoſes the others puniſhment. And here two Queries naturally ariſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why God ſhould defer to the laſt His diſtinguiſhing care of his People, and not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them his Bleſſings in a <hi>bright courſe</hi> of his Providence?</p>
            <p n="2">2. In what reſpects a diſtinctneſs of End be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes viſible to an Obſerver?</p>
            <p>In anſwer to the Firſt, concerning God's delays of diſtinguiſhing his People, ſome alledge the abſoluteneſs of his Dominion, as a moſt ſatisfying
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54597:8"/>ground for ſuch a diſpoſal. But here the doubt ſtill returns: For Dominion may be a Rule to <hi>ſubject</hi> our Wills, but not to <hi>ſettle</hi> our Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. The Mind of Man is too free to be bound up with that Notion, and ſtill ſeeks to enquire further. What then will fully ſatisfie it in its ſearch? It muſt be convinced of the Juſtice and Wiſdom of his Proceedings; for theſe are two Attributes that ſtrike our <hi>Reaſon</hi> with the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of their luſtre, and can ſilence the cavils of a Diſputer. If then his Juſtice and Wiſdom may be made out for appointing ſuch a way, no room is left for any ſcruple to get in.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Juſtice reſpects us</hi> in its exerciſe, whereas <hi>Power</hi> is but a <hi>Miniſter</hi> to him that uſes it. And how Juſtice reſpects us will appear, in that our corrupt Natures require the method of an Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the Principle of Grace (there infus'd) needs ſharp proofs to corroborate it in its acts, and to teſtifie its ſoundneſs to the World.</p>
            <p>He that will but conſider the corruption of our Natures, how deeply printed their <hi>ſtains</hi> are, and by what a ſinfulneſs of practice farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; muſt needs conclude, that thoſe Evils we ſuffer are truly <hi>penal;</hi> and conſequently our meriting of the ſcourge, acquits our Judge from the tyranny of inflicting it. The Rod that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles our carnal <hi>ſtrength,</hi> it loads too our <hi>conſciences</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54597:9"/>with its burden; and tells us when we are bruiſed, that we have <hi>guilt</hi> likewiſe, to compleat the miſery of our torment. God, <hi>who is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works,</hi> brings no pain upon any of us, but what our own ſins duly deſerve: The <hi>ſtorm</hi> comes from <hi>above;</hi> but it is ſome <hi>vapour below,</hi> that has bred it. Earth and Man's heart are alike fatal in their productions; they nouriſh in them the <hi>ſeeds</hi> of a tempeſt, and ſending them up towards <hi>Heaven,</hi> darken that Region where they come, and turn its <hi>influence</hi> to oppreſs us. Upon this account, none of us can repine or tax God's dealings, that will but ſeverely examin himſelf, and read the ſinfulneſs of his own actings; whence he may ſoon pick a Comment, out of the blackneſs of that Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to expound and interpret the ſad accidents of his life, as a convincing Argument of God's Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Again, the Principle of Grace (infus'd into our Natures) does juſtly exact the diſcipline of ſuffering; that ſo it may grow up and ſpread in our Souls, under the benefit of that tryal; and ſhow the Divineneſs of its original, by all the <hi>hardſhip</hi> of perſeverance. Faith, Hope, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, abide weak in their <hi>infancy,</hi> when untryed; and (which is another reproach to that ſtate) the truth too of their <hi>birth</hi> is ſuſpected. Nothing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54597:9"/>gives the ſpiritual Man ſuch life and vigour as a <hi>temptation:</hi> Not that <hi>of it ſelf</hi> it can cauſe <hi>either,</hi> but <hi>occaſionally</hi> it conduces to his improvement; for affording him the matter of a reſiſtance, his <hi>Graces</hi> are thereby quicken'd and rais'd; and when the temptation is beaten off, their <hi>true birth from Heaven</hi> is diſcover'd by the nobleneſs of their Conqueſt. So then, thoſe temporal evils God ſends, are to be reckon'd no otherwiſe, than a <hi>juſt diet</hi> He preſcribes; their ends and uſes are proper to the Patient; whereby the equity of the Sender is always preſerv'd, though the <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> many times that conveys them, contracts <hi>guilt</hi> in the Service. Where now is the wrong offer'd a Saint, if vaſt rewards be deſign'd, and croſſes only decreed to fit and prepare him? He that can complain here of Injuſtice, may as well complain of hard ſeaſons that ripen fruits, or the laying of <hi>Iſaac</hi> under the <hi>knife,</hi> which ſecur'd the <hi>Inheritance</hi> to the Child.</p>
            <p>As God's Juſtice is thus cleer'd; ſo his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is no leſs evident, in the appointment of thoſe troubles in life before mentioned.</p>
            <p>For it is an act of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to ſute wages with works; and ſo Heaven being the higheſt pay, He wiſely exacts from us the higheſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. But this in <hi>ſuffering</hi> conſiſts; which as it is the beſt proof of our love to God, ſo the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54597:10"/>moſt eminent mark of our courage; by how much the greater difficulty we undergo of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing our fears, and keeping our ſelves firm and immoveable in a good purpoſe. Upon this ſcore of difficulty it is, that <hi>paſsive valour</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly preferred before <hi>active;</hi> as giving us lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger proofs of a generous reſolution in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter. For to him that ſuffers, evil is <hi>preſent,</hi> and thereby ſharper upon his mind; nay it is farther edg'd in its ſharpneſs, by ſeeming to come from the <hi>ſtronger party;</hi> which makes the force of it more terrible; laſt of all, <hi>length of time</hi> is required for the exerciſe, wherein Nature is apt to flag and diſſolve; ſo that here three diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements lye in his way, which yet he coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly breaks thorough: And they are, <hi>ſenſe of evil; opinion of his enemy;</hi> and a <hi>weariſome trouble of the time.</hi> But none of theſe are found in him that <hi>briskly</hi> attempts danger; who regards evil as <hi>future,</hi> and ſo removes the ſmart of its ſting; who with the mind of a <hi>ſuperiour</hi> ſets on it, and ſo learns before hand to contemn it; laſtly, who needs but a <hi>ſudden heat</hi> to evidence his courage; and ſo keeps freſh his ſpirits in the employ. Here then lyes the advantage of a Martyrs ſuffering, that he has every thing to daunt him in his cauſe; whereas the Heroes of this World find eaſineſs in their hazards, which leſſens the glory of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54597:10"/>triumph. Hence God wiſely puts us to that noble tryal of bearing the Croſs, and ſo follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Lord; which being the utmoſt pitch of our reſolution for his Service, Happineſs is duly rated by that price He demands.</p>
            <p>But there remains a ſecond Query to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, <hi>viz.</hi> in what reſpects a diſtinctneſs of End becomes viſible to an Obſerver.</p>
            <p>For, 1. Peace in this place cannot be limitted to a temporal deliverance, though Man ſeems properly the judge of it; and Scripture too af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords ſome pregnant inſtances of thoſe happy periods of an Affliction: So <hi>Noah</hi> was freed from the toſſings of the <hi>flood,</hi> and (like his <hi>Ark)</hi> reſted in peace: So <hi>Joſeph</hi> was taken from the pit and the dungeon, to end his days near the Majeſty of a Throne; and <hi>David</hi> (the Author of this Pſalm) could experimentally confirm the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a change: Others too I might reckon up, that had a ſenſible taſte of God's Promiſes before they were ſummoned to their graves. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhould we admit it in a ſenſe ſo reſtrained, we muſt exclude out of our proſpect whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Saints, that neither <hi>knew, nor would accept deliverance,</hi> that <hi>they might obtain a better reſurrection.</hi> And where is the remarkable end of theſe, or what pompous finiſhing of their lives, without you'll ſay <hi>Swords and Axes</hi> made it up, and the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54597:11"/>
               <hi>Heroick Courage</hi> of the Expecters? Either then we muſt take it in a wider Notion, or poorly limit it to a few; where right is not ſo much done them in a <hi>record</hi> of God's Bleſſings, as injury to others by our <hi>ſilence.</hi> And as a bare temporal deliverance is not here meant, ſo neither, in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Can we reſtrain it to Immortality of Bliſs; for though that contain in it all the <hi>ſubſtance of peace,</hi> yet being an <hi>inviſible reward,</hi> it is above the conſideration of our outward man; therefore we muſt take it in the wideſt extent, where both the <hi>Eye of Faith</hi> and the <hi>Eye of Senſe</hi> may joyn in the teſtimony.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Eye of Faith,</hi> it is moſt open and cleer when the End of the Righteous is come. His Death gives it a quiet view, and the <hi>darkneſs</hi> of the <hi>Scene</hi> is removed by the <hi>light of Eternity</hi> breaking in. While he <hi>ſleeps,</hi> it awakes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully expatiates over his Joys; for it is now like a Mariner ſet on ſhore, and ſtands ſafe upon fixt ground, whereas Shipwracks at Sea did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſturb the apprehenſion; ſo that it can with a compoſedneſs of thought contemplate his <hi>Bliſs,</hi> anſwerable to the ſoftneſs of his repoſe. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſtractions it might meet with in his life, they are all <hi>buried</hi> with the Sufferer; the doubts and ſcruples are taken away; and no more is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54597:11"/>God's care of him called in queſtion, ſince it ſees him as it were put in poſſeſſion of a glorious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. Thus a Saints deceaſe procures a double liberty; firſt to himſelf, from the fetters of a calamity; next to the Faith of a Beholder, from the prejudices of the World.</p>
            <p>But is the <hi>Eye of Senſe</hi> alike capable of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction? And can we be entertain'd in our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man with a true pleaſure of beholding him? We all readily grant it upon the ſight of a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and a ſucceſsful cloſe of the righteous Man's days. None ſtumbles at Providence in that <hi>Sun-ſhine;</hi> nay his bare <hi>ſetting in light</hi> has that ſtrength of luſtre, as to reflect it back upon his paſt troubles. But how can the Spectator be ſecured from falling, while he is viewing the Act of ſome black Tragedy; when the vail of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is drawn over a Saint, and he ſeems to be given up from above to the luſt of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies! To ſtand in that caſe ſeems very hard, by reaſon of the ſadneſs of the ſpectacle. And yet even here, if we would take but direction, we may ſtill ſafely look on; becauſe there is proper matter for Senſe to regard, and from thence to form the Notion of Peace.</p>
            <p>And this is grounded upon a threefold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque:
<list>
                  <item>1. Of the Cauſe.</item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54597:12"/>
                  <item>2. Of the Manner.</item>
                  <item>3. Of the Conſequences of his End.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Cauſe</hi> has a <hi>brightneſs</hi> in it to ſtrike our Senſes, when we ſee Truth and Juſtice, Religion and Piety, ſingly maintain'd; and the Seal of Martyrdom cheerfully embraced in the midſt of terrours from an <hi>armed multitude,</hi> where <hi>Power and Victory</hi> might be <hi>Pleaders</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> but <hi>Blood and Sacriledge</hi> the <hi>Overthrowers.</hi> And ſo the <hi>primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Confeſſors</hi> powerfully convinced the Heathen World, by a ſingle maintenance of their Cauſe. Alone they <hi>triumphed</hi> in what they profeſſed, becauſe alone they ſtood up Champions to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; whence thoſe that ſaw them, fell from viewing to wonder, from wonder to love; and love eaſily ended in their Converſion. Neither is this inſtance reſtrained to thoſe times, but every Age can produce one; and let God's Call but warrant <hi>the like appearance,</hi> the goodneſs of a <hi>Chriſtian profeſsion,</hi> as it will arm a <hi>Saint</hi> to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, ſo it will juſtifie him to any enemy, by the conſtancy of his <hi>defending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, the <hi>manner</hi> is viſible, when we ſee in the <hi>Witneſſer meekneſs</hi> and <hi>charity, faith</hi> and <hi>devotion</hi> match'd and joyn'd; which ſpeak of themſelves a <hi>tranquillity</hi> of mind, a <hi>compaſsion</hi> for Sinners, a <hi>conſcience</hi> of Glory, and laſtly a <hi>fitneſs</hi> for Heaven. A ſtout defence is nothing, without Grace to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54597:12"/>accompany it; for both Hiſtory and Experience can furniſh us with Examples of the vanity of that <hi>ſign;</hi> but where Grace does attend, it then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes proclaimer of a <hi>good confeſsion;</hi> it erects a <hi>Scaffold</hi> for <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>martyrdom</hi> together. And ſo the Saints of old, by the manner of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prov'd the gloriouſneſs of their End. A <hi>heavenly flame</hi> appeared in their acts, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the Spectator to look upward when they dyed. And this kind of Religious Spirit all true <hi>Martyrs</hi> are endued with; therefore to behold them in their laſt <hi>part,</hi> with what piety they manage it, according to the rules of their Bleſſed Saviour, is to be alike convinced of the truth of their ſtate, and what a Kingdom above is prepar'd to receive them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>conſequence</hi> will declare it; when we ſee the <hi>upright Man's Name</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity flouriſh;</hi> and the concern of <hi>Juſtice</hi> in his <hi>revenge,</hi> firſt by a <hi>general confuſion</hi> of things, afterwards by a ſignal <hi>puniſhment</hi> of his <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> Pillars and Monuments being every where built upon the Ruins of his Adverſaries, to direct us in our Gaze, and confirm us in this Truth, That <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> alone has the <hi>Authority of Execution,</hi> when the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of its <hi>Defender</hi> is gone. If now other Ages we cannot recur to for one perfect Inſtance in every particular, our own can richly afford it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54597:13"/>us; for we find the <hi>conſequences</hi> cleerly <hi>exemplified</hi> in our <hi>late Prince,</hi> as well as the <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of his <hi>End;</hi> ſo that the Demonſtration here is compleat, and the very Eye of Senſe can bring in its teſtimony, that <hi>the end of the righteous is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not be thought to anticipate the Faſt, which by a particular <hi>accident</hi> is removed; but I am ſure the Day of the Fact, and your own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, no accident can change. This is that <hi>Fatal Time,</hi> wherein a Glorious <hi>Martyr</hi> prepared for Sacrifice, with all thoſe Ornaments of Virtue that either a <hi>Soveraign</hi> or a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> could put on; and a bloody Enemy ſeemed over him to prevail, with all thoſe Crimes that <hi>Rebellion</hi> or <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> can contain: Therefore by mentioning the time now, I do but pay it its due debt, and prepare your humiliation for the morrow.</p>
            <p>It is not for me to attempt His Character, whoſe Life was the exact <hi>Tranſcript</hi> of His Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; His Government, the <hi>repreſentative</hi> of His Goodneſs; His Writings <hi>Princely,</hi> as if the Pen were His <hi>Scepter;</hi> but withall humble and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, as if none had offended Him; laſtly, His Sufferings all along a lively Expreſſion of <hi>Chriſtian Graces,</hi> and a full Argument in themſelves to reveal the righteouſneſs of his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>As little can I deſcribe the guilt of His <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54597:13"/>whoſe <hi>Inſpirations</hi> were <hi>killing;</hi> their <hi>Faſts</hi> but a <hi>Solemnity to devour;</hi> who mixt their breach of Divine Law with the mockery of its Maker; and to ſhow wickedneſs was ripe, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of ſinning invaded that Head, where the <hi>Oyl</hi> one would think were enough to protect it from danger. All that they could poſſibly boaſt of, was the current of proſperity for ſome time. But Chriſtian Obſervers ſhould weigh their End, as the Heathen Votaries did not mind the <hi>Garlands</hi> about the Heads of their Beaſts, but the <hi>Altars</hi> they were led to: They might indeed (like thoſe <hi>Victims) break looſe</hi> for a while, but could not properly be ſaid to ſhare in a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: The Peace they enjoy'd was but a <hi>diſturb'd ſlumber</hi> before death, but an <hi>unpleaſant Feaſt</hi> before <hi>Execution.</hi> Who can have confidence to affirm, That <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (who drowned ſo many <hi>Infants</hi>) had yet redemption from <hi>plagues,</hi> when an <hi>expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory deluge</hi> was to ſucceed? Or that <hi>Ahab</hi> (who could ſwallow a poor Man's <hi>Vineyard</hi> at a <hi>Faſt,</hi> and cruelly mingled the <hi>blood of the grape</hi> with the <hi>blood of him that owned it)</hi> had yet peace in his days, when an <hi>Arrow</hi> was made ſharp to pierce him? No more can we call thoſe <hi>Victories</hi> Mercies, that were conſtantly waited on by greater judgments; and we find by the Fall of thoſe that had them, that to build <hi>impious Trophies</hi> upon the <hi>Graves</hi> of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54597:14"/>
               <hi>Princes</hi> is to build upon <hi>ſacred ground,</hi> that will <hi>ſink</hi> them.</p>
            <p>But paſſing by this Subject, I come now to infer ſome uſeful Truths from a general beholding of ſuch Examples. And here I ſhall ſhow
<list>
                  <item>1. The neceſſity of converting our ſpeculation into a Religious Practice.</item>
                  <item>2. The benefit of being upright betimes in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our Peace.</item>
                  <item>3. The folly of Irreligion, whereby a future peace is utterly excluded; neither has it a preſent one for its reward.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The neceſſity of converting our ſpeculation into a Religious Practice.</p>
            <p>When the Pſalmiſt bids us to <hi>mark the upright,</hi> it is not a meer direction to our eyes, but to our ſteps likewiſe; and our gaze little avails us, if if it reform not the lookers on. The <hi>Chriſtian Watch-tower</hi> is quite different from the Worlds; there the <hi>Watchman</hi> ſtands fixt, viewing his ſpace, and lazily meaſuring the courſe of another; and the <hi>reports</hi> which are brought to him from <hi>ſenſe,</hi> never alter his poſture begun: But here we are bound to <hi>turn</hi> and <hi>move,</hi> labour and ſtrive in our Office of <hi>obſerving;</hi> firſt advance our Reaſon to ſee the race, and then work our Wills to purſue it. Indeed a <hi>bare ſpeculation</hi> is meer ſoleciſm in Religion; a work contradictory to the main end:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54597:14"/>We abſurdly ſet againſt the deſigns of <hi>Providence,</hi> if we uſe not Inſtances to promote Piety, and the ſcope of his <hi>Laws,</hi> if our <hi>light</hi> be not ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to guide us in duty.</p>
            <p>God in his <hi>Government</hi> abroad, leaves exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary proofs, to train us up for his Service; and by expreſs Commands in his <hi>Word,</hi> farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces the obligation; therefore a <hi>naked Theory</hi> of things is ſo far from becoming an ornament to our Natures, that it rather increaſes their <hi>guilt,</hi> by a flat reſiſting of his Will.</p>
            <p>I know the <hi>contemplative</hi> powers <hi>enlarge</hi> our <hi>Souls;</hi> but they are the <hi>active</hi> that <hi>better</hi> them; the former give them the <hi>ſubtilty</hi> of <hi>ſpirits,</hi> but the latter crown them with <hi>goodneſs.</hi> And it is goodneſs alone that qualifies us for Heaven; whereas ſubtilty may belong to the <hi>Angels con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned;</hi> who retain their height of <hi>diſcerning,</hi> as another addition to their plague; for they reap nothing by it, but a fuller ſenſe of their pains. Would we then give our Theory a right advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Practice with it muſt be joyned: It is to no purpoſe to glory in <hi>marking and beholding,</hi> when it cannot ſeparate us from Hell.</p>
            <p>They are but Falſe-Prophets, that <hi>ſee</hi> and are not obedient to the <hi>Viſion;</hi> ſo they are but Falſe-Profeſſors, and will finally periſh in deceiving their own Souls, that conſider the upright Man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54597:15"/>in his ways, but are never wrought to imitation. <hi>Balaam</hi> we read could get up to a <hi>high mountain,</hi> that he might <hi>ſee the utmoſt part</hi> of God's <hi>Iſrael:</hi> From the <hi>top of the rocks he ſaw,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.</note> 
               <hi>and from the hills he beheld them:</hi> But taking the <hi>coldneſs</hi> and <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs</hi> of his <hi>ſtation,</hi> he was utterly loſt in that view; when it filled him with delight, but not with love; chain'd up his fancy, but left his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſtill free. But whoever aſcends <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> he aſcends a <hi>fruitfull Hill:</hi> He contemplates the righteous in their path, and by treading that path, enriches his proſpect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The benefit of being upright betimes in order to our Peace.</p>
            <p>Peace is a ſummary of all Bleſſings, a moſt comprehenſive word to denote the Perfection of our ſtate; and being particularly referr'd to our <hi>end,</hi> it implyes the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of our Happineſs. Now the <hi>perfection of our ſtate</hi> is in nothing more furthered, than in an early following the righteous Man's way; ſince it creates a <hi>preſent,</hi> and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhes too our <hi>future</hi> repoſe. As for the <hi>preſent</hi> Good we enjoy, it is perhaps unknown to the reſt of the World, becauſe it lyes deep in our Souls, and their workings we know are inviſible to others; yet however the foundation of our quiet abides the ſame; and it lyes in an effectual <hi>reſtraining</hi> of our unbridled <hi>deſires,</hi> in a powerful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54597:15"/>
               <hi>aſſwaging</hi> of our <hi>griefs</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> and a thorough <hi>purging</hi> off the <hi>guilt</hi> of our <hi>conſciences.</hi> All theſe advantages a timely uprightneſs brings with it; and every Saint may diſcern them in himſelf; which is a ſufficient allay to his outward troubles. What an eaſe muſt this be in the midſt of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to look within, and find there every thing <hi>ſtill</hi> and <hi>cleer,</hi> the <hi>affections</hi> being calm'd, and the <hi>enditements</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> made void? Nay, this is not all; but God comes in with the conſolations of his Grace, to feed and refreſh the inward man; ſo that could the World here make an inſpection, it would be forced to confeſs of the perfect <hi>Walker,</hi> that not only his <hi>end,</hi> but all his <hi>progreſs</hi> is <hi>peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us next conſider his <hi>future</hi> ſettlement, where you may behold him even in his death-bed (as if it were the <hi>ſtage</hi> of his <hi>triumph)</hi> how undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he encounters the terrour of what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, with all the pleaſure of a reflection. And he is ſupported in it two ways:
<list>
                  <item>1. He knows the ſpring of his repentance was pure in its firſt riſe, which begets an <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That he has the teſtimony of after-fruits to confirm it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whence he joyfully meets that <hi>grim Serjeant,</hi> and while he is haling him forcibly to <hi>reſt,</hi> he excuſes the <hi>roughneſs</hi> of the ſeizure.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54597:16"/>
            <p> But this <hi>peaceable</hi> kind of ſpirit a <hi>late penitent</hi> is deprived of, as he is of all <hi>honour</hi> in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. For in <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>reſpects</hi> his comfort fails, when in the <hi>pangs</hi> of extremity he ſeeks his God; though through the mercy of that God he may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>His firſt diſcouragement is, that he knows not the purity of the <hi>ſpring,</hi> whence his repentance proceeds; nor can certainly conclude, that it is a <hi>filial love,</hi> but rather a <hi>ſlaviſh fear,</hi> that is the principle of the <hi>current.</hi> For Death he ſees is before him, and all thoſe evils that accompany it; whence he may well doubt thoſe tears to be <hi>falſe</hi> which flow from him, and deſtructive too in their falſhood, by a <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of his Soul. And is not this want of evidence ſufficiently tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, though the Soul ſhould be priviledged with happineſs, ſince thereby all ſenſe of it is gone, and the <hi>ſting</hi> only retained of paſt pleaſures? While in the mean time, the upright Liver con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues down his <hi>peace</hi> by a <hi>regiſter</hi> of his actings, and brings at the very laſt gaſp a full and entire ſpirit to cloſe with his apprehenſion of coming Joyes.</p>
            <p>His next diſcouragement is, that an after-teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>good fruits</hi> is cut off, to confirm him in his fears. For how can ſuch a teſtimony be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, when he preſently dyes after repenting?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54597:16"/>Whence ſuſpicions muſt needs ariſe, and his Death be ſurrounded with <hi>dark ſhadows,</hi> becauſe no ſpace is left him to prove the ſincerity of a good purpoſe. And what an Agony muſt a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of this kind be (how gracious ſoever God be in accepting) when the paſt ſins, we reflect on, terrifie our minds, and a future up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs is denied us? whereas the perfect Man has the <hi>credit</hi> and <hi>ſupport</hi> of a <hi>good ſtock</hi> before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and improving it all along to his Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, he can quickly rely upon Divine Mercy, as pardoning his frailties, and expecting no longer proofs of obedience. If then we value the Peace of Conſcience as well as the other of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, holineſs of Life muſt be antecedent, for the better compaſſing of our end.</p>
            <p>It remains I ſhould ſhow in the third place,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The folly of <hi>Irreligion,</hi> whereby a <hi>future peace</hi> is utterly excluded; neither has it a <hi>preſent</hi> one for its reward. Now the <hi>Folly</hi> of it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, ſince it neither diſcovers a <hi>life</hi> of <hi>reaſon,</hi> which provides for good in the <hi>ſucceſsion;</hi> no nor a <hi>life</hi> of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> which provides for an <hi>immediate gratifying</hi> of our Wills. The <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> of <hi>good</hi> is cut off, when our <hi>future happineſs</hi> is obſtructed; and an <hi>immediate gratifying</hi> of us is denied, while <hi>war</hi> continues in the Soul. How then can there be wiſdom in the purſuit of Impiety, where
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54597:17"/>there is neither <hi>hope</hi> to tempt, nor <hi>enjoyment</hi> to ſatisfie! The Object of a Man's <hi>choice</hi> muſt be either ſome <hi>preſent</hi> or <hi>future</hi> pleaſure; the <hi>paſt</hi> is not, becauſe not poſſible to be enjoyed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when no time can adminiſter delight in a courſe of ſin, what motive is there in it to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure us?</p>
            <p>As to the poſſibility of attaining to <hi>future peace</hi> in a vicious cuſtome, it is confeſſedly diſowned by the <hi>profane;</hi> who are convinced, that their want of <hi>Title</hi> does ſufficiently baffle their <hi>Plea;</hi> all they can pretend to is the <hi>preſent;</hi> and here lyes the <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>ſins deceit,</hi> that it colours an evil with ſuch <hi>paint,</hi> as to hide it from him that <hi>laid</hi> it on.</p>
            <p>Man <hi>carnally reaſons</hi> for the corruptions of his life, and forgets the <hi>falſhood</hi> of their <hi>covering.</hi> He paſſes by the madneſs of courting a <hi>moment,</hi> and conſiders not the <hi>laſtingneſs</hi> of its <hi>puniſhment.</hi> What then is Conſcience wholly dead, that it ſhould not wound the Evil-doer? Has it quite loſt its edge or activity in his Soul? Why then does it ſo generally invade Mankind, <hi>perplex</hi> their Spirits in fulfilling of their luſts, <hi>rack</hi> them in all their ſenſual delights, and <hi>grow</hi> upon their <hi>pains,</hi> like a freſh <hi>Executioner?</hi> For ſo is the force of it prov'd in the World; and to break their <hi>peace</hi> in the commiſſion of ſin, <hi>two Images</hi> haunt them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54597:17"/>(of an equal terrour) <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of his <hi>Throne.</hi> All then a Sinner can expect at beſt is but a <hi>ſhort ſuſpence</hi> of his trouble; and whether the ſuſpence be not a greater act of hoſtility from his Judge, he may well queſtion. There is no tempeſt ſo hurtful as the calm before it; where the <hi>face</hi> of danger is <hi>ſmoothed</hi> up, and death ſuddenly conveyed.
<note place="margin">Judg. 4.1</note> 
               <hi>Jael's bottle of milk</hi> was more deſtructive to <hi>Siſera,</hi> than the <hi>hammer in her hand:</hi> For by giving him that drink, ſhe laid him faſt aſleep to be ſlain.</p>
            <p>But beſides <hi>pangs</hi> of mind, and a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Lethargy,</hi> if they be wanting; let the wicked Man ſhow any colour for <hi>peace,</hi> by being fill'd with what he enjoys. Behold! he is as much a ſtranger to an <hi>eaſe</hi> of <hi>fulneſs,</hi> as he is to a <hi>reſt</hi> of <hi>deſire;</hi> ſo that there is <hi>war</hi> in his very Feaſts, to which he ſeems moſt cheerfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. Nothing of the Creature can ſatisfie him, and therefore every thing is his diſturber; he wanders for good, and finds none; he craves variety of Objects, and is puniſhed by doing ſo: For he is thereby diſtracted in his choice, and has all the <hi>labour</hi> of an <hi>uncertainty.</hi> Go now and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the pleaſures of ſin; <hi>Walk in the ways of thy heart,</hi> and <hi>in the ſight of thine eyes;</hi> but withall tell me at the ſame time, whether thou haſt true cauſe of rejoycing, when thou treadeſt a <hi>fools
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54597:18"/>maze,</hi> and art wretchedly loſt in thoſe <hi>turns</hi> and <hi>windings,</hi> which thy own appetite has contrived. Above all call to mind what <hi>ſubſtantial peace</hi> is neglected by thee, I mean thoſe vaſt and ſolid joyes in another World, to which a loſs in this is nothing comparable; how thou <hi>bartereſt</hi> away thy Soul for a <hi>luſt,</hi> and pawneſt <hi>eternity</hi> for a <hi>moment;</hi> as if thy great ſtrife were for nothing elſe, but to compleat the Character of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>I need no more inſiſt on this Subject, and ſhall therefore beg leave more particularly to make Application.</p>
            <p>To be ſpeedily Religious is the higheſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to our ſelves; nay (to add ſomewhat more) our beſt <hi>homage</hi> to <hi>Princes.</hi> For we thereby ſecure to them their Peace, and eſtabliſh their Throne; we encompaſs them about with God's Bleſſings, and bring Heavenly Forces to their Cauſe. But National Sins raiſe Storms, ſet up <hi>Hills</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to plant <hi>battery</hi> againſt that very <hi>Seat,</hi> which God has fixt by his <hi>Power.</hi> Nothing ſo <hi>traiterous</hi> as <hi>Vice,</hi> nor ſo <hi>diſloyal</hi> as <hi>Iniquity;</hi> and we have all ſadly experimented the efficacy of its <hi>treaſon,</hi> wherein vile Inſtruments had never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over ſuch <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> but that <hi>general guilt</hi> was their <hi>Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who now, that conſiders the advancement of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54597:18"/>holy living, will not contribute what he can to his own, nay his Princes Glory; endeavour as a Chriſtian to <hi>purchaſe</hi> a <hi>Crown,</hi> and as a Chriſtian to defend one? In the mean while, let no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of proſperous ſinning tempt us to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of any corruption; for all proſperity of that kind is but the <hi>guilding</hi> of a <hi>ſtorm;</hi> where God hides the Evil He intends, that He might double Men's ruin by the ſurpriſe. It was a true ſaying (though <hi>Jezabel</hi> ſpoke it) <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace that ſlew his Maſter?</hi> So Men may thoroughly execute the worſt Crimes, but that liberty allowed them is their plague; and their want of peace (as the conſequent of their deeds) is a ſufficient motive to diſſwade them.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhould any be terrified with thoſe croſſes, which are many times the portion of God's Children. For how ſharp ſoever they be, yet they cannot null the force of His promiſe: The promiſe ſecures them from overthrow, though not from ſuffering. It is like that <hi>Bow</hi> in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> ſet by God for a token of peace; <hi>Showers</hi> indeed do accompany it, but no <hi>Deluge.</hi> And O that we would conſider the reward of <hi>inward peace,</hi> which is ſafely lodg'd in a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience! where the mind delightfully views its own acts, and calms the <hi>paſsions</hi> in the ſurvey; where a <hi>victory</hi> over ſin is followed with <hi>triumph,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54597:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and a purſuit of good with the <hi>reſt</hi> of <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> where the accidents of life do not ſhake, and <hi>Providence</hi> is a Sanctuary from trouble: In a word, where <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelf is ſet up in all the <hi>light, beauty,</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of its frame. Therefore ſince no Plea is left for commiſſion of ſin, but all encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given us to duty, with what <hi>judgment</hi> ſhould we <hi>behold,</hi> and with what <hi>affection tranſcribe</hi> the <hi>perfect man;</hi> that reſembling him here, we may finiſh that likeneſs in another World, and find that uprightneſs (which is the peace of our Souls) will be the peace too of our Perſons in a Bleſſed Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, be Praiſe and Honour for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is newly publiſhed two <hi>Recantation-Sermons</hi> (Preached at the <hi>French</hi> Church in the <hi>Savoy</hi> by two Converted <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> Mr. <hi>De la Motte,</hi> late Preacher of the Order of the <hi>Carmelites;</hi> and Mr. <hi>De Luzanzy,</hi> Licentiat in Divinity;) wherein the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are laid open and confuted. Both printed in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſold by <hi>Moſes Pitt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
